Hey everybody, welcome to
the content video going
over section 4.2 of your
textbook defining functions.
Now something that whenever
we start a new chapter in the
book I fail to do is go over
the introduction section.
You guys are more than welcome
to kind of read the outline and
objective section of each of the
chapters, but I usually just jump
right into the ones that start
working on code. So if you're
interested in why we always start
at like the point two, that's why.
Okay, so functions. This is a
great concept to learn when you're
working with anything in Python or
any code really because at some point
in your code you're going to want
to be able to do something that
isn't built in. So let me give you
a quick analogy about functions.
So we call tons and tons and
tons of built-in functions like
print, float, they list a couple
of them here, len, min, max,
There's like hundreds of these
functions that we call all the time
and they do really great and useful
stuff for us. But like it says in
our textbook, sometimes you're going
to want to have something custom
for a specific purpose, right?
So this is sometimes like when I
go to Walmart and I don't know why
I picked Walmart. I go to stores
looking for like the perfect pair
of jeans, right? And like I can't
find the perfect pair of jeans at
any store. So I just buy some denim,
get a pattern and I make them myself.
They're custom, right? So same
kind of idea here with functions
is that sometimes we have specific
things that we just want to do
and want to have operate in our
algorithm, but it doesn't make sense
to have it be built using the built
-in methods of Python. And sometimes
it's nice to be able to have
something that you can call over
and over and over again so that you
don't have to, like, write out a
ton of code every time you want to
do the same process. So let me kind
of walk you through an example.
And maybe we'll just do this one.
Well, I'll walk you through the
example. So here's one where they
are defining a function that will
square a number, right? and when we
square a number we do something
like this here let me just we say
you know square is equal to two
raised to the power of two we could
do that again right square again
equal or sorry sine to the value of
two it's the power actually that's
cubed so we'll just write cubed
And we could go one more, we could, I
don't know what to the fourth power is,
fourth,
two,
raise to the power of four, right?
But it does get a little bit
tiring, like, writing all of this
out. Okay, so one thing that they're
using as an example is, they're
saying, here is a function where you
can just put in a number, and it
will raise that number to the second
power, right? and that means you
could run this function any number
of times just like how we run
the print function or the min max
whatever function you could run
this function over and over and over
and over again on any number and
it will do the same thing for it.
So to create a function
you need a couple of pieces
you You need a name,
you need arguments, you
need the main body of logic,
and you need a return.
So what this looks like is if I
was to create a function that would
square a number, I would define it,
and this is the syntax, you say def
or definition, and then you name
your function. I would call this one
square or maybe I'd call it square
two numbers square or I don't know
actually no I would just call it
square because that makes the most
sense and if I am going to square a
number I need the number I want to
square all right you use a colon so
that anything that comes after it
gets indented so it's within the
scope of the function definition so
I'll say let's take the number and
we will set it or assign it the value
of or sorry we don't want the
number we want the square like a new
variable square is equal to the
number raised to the power of two and
then we will return square let's
actually name it something else so it's
not the same name as our function
name we'll call it square num turn
square num so check out what
happens when I print out square.
You guessed it. Nothing happened, right?
And check out why. Type error
square is missing one required
positional argument number. So
it's saying, hey, I can't do
anything because you didn't
give me an argument. You didn't
give me the number I was
expecting. So let's put in seven.
I think that's the one
they use in the textbook.
And outcomes, oh, there
it is, 49. All Let's run
this again, but let's
run it on 10 this time.
We would expect to see 100, and we do.
Here's something worth noting.
What happens if I just run square
on 5?
We don't get the result outputted.
Why not? Well, it's because
we're not printing the result.
So is 5 being squared? Yes, it is
being squared, because we are calling
this function that we defined,
so 5 is getting fed into this
function definition, and then
the number 5 is getting squared
and assigned to the value of square
num, and then square num is
being returned, but it's like the
number is being returned and then
we don't do anything with it.
But check out this. I could say
result is equal to square of five
and then I could say result plus
equals four and then print results.
Result is now 29. Why is it 29?
Well it's because it was 25 once I
squared five but then I added
four to it, right? So once we have
a variable of a returning from a
function we can return it to our
code and then that's what the
return statement does. It throws the
variable back to us that we can
then do more things with it. So
this becomes useful because now we
have a function that we can call
as many times as we want. So I
could say for I in range a thousand
print square and we'll just do it on I.
And we should see some
numbers that get pretty
big pretty fast, right?
These are the numbers that
we're squaring, and they
are already in like the
600,000s. So pretty cool. And
that's kind of the idea of defining
a custom function. So one thing
you might be asking is, well,
why would I do any of that?
Because I could just as easily
square the number. And while that's
true, for these examples that
I'm showing you, it's pretty
straightforward, and you probably
wouldn't need to define a
function just to square a number.
But we do get into some pretty
complicated algorithms, especially
as we code more and more and
as you get out into industry.
You get into examples that are
just not feasible to be writing out
10 different times for, you know,
very small changes to be made.
And so that's where functions
become really, really helpful is
because they're a set of code, a
block of code that will be the same
every single time it gets run. You
shouldn't have any bugs or errors,
which I actually don't remember
if the textbook talks about, but
there's a bunch of reasons that
using a function is really, really
great. One of them is modularity.
So it helps us to break up our
code into specific modules and
helps us to have specific little
elements that we can reuse over
and over. It helps with debugging.
So that, you know, if I know
that this function is working
perfectly, there's probably and
there's something still wrong
with my code. The problem is
somewhere outside of the function.
It also helps us with
readability of our code. I'm not
seeing any of these things
in here, but they're probably
in here somewhere. I'm just
saying them off my memory.
So, yeah, readability of our code
functions really help with readability.
And I think there's a couple of
other benefits as well that I
can't remember off the top of my
head. But really, it's good for
reusability of code and, yeah,
breaking things into smaller, easier
chunks that are better situated for
specific use cases. So that's going
to wrap up everything for this
content video. Thanks for watching.